<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="hyprland_ctm_control_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2024 Vaxry
    All rights reserved.

    Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without
    modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions are met:

    1. Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright notice, this
       list of conditions and the following disclaimer.

    2. Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright notice,
       this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the documentation
       and/or other materials provided with the distribution.

    3. Neither the name of the copyright holder nor the names of its
       contributors may be used to endorse or promote products derived from
       this software without specific prior written permission.

    THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS "AS IS"
    AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE
    IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE
    DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT HOLDER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE
    FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL
    DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR
    SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER
    CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY,
    OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE
    OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="controlling outputs' color transform matrix">
    This protocol allows a client to control outputs' color transform matrix (CTM).

    This protocol is privileged and should not be exposed to unprivileged clients.
  </description>

  <interface name="hyprland_ctm_control_manager_v1" version="2">
    <description summary="manager to control CTMs">
      This object is a manager which offers requests to control CTMs.

      If any changes are done, once this object is destroyed, CTMs are reset back to
      an identity matrix.
    </description>

    <request name="set_ctm_for_output">
      <description summary="set the CTM of an output">
        Set a CTM for a wl_output.

        This state is not applied immediately; clients must call .commit to
        apply any pending changes.

        The provided values describe a 3x3 Row-Major CTM with values in the range of [0, ∞)

        Passing values outside of the range will raise an invalid_matrix error.

        The default value of the CTM is an identity matrix.

        If an output doesn't get a CTM set with set_ctm_for_output and commit is called,
        that output will get its CTM reset to an identity matrix.
      </description>
      <arg name="output" type="object" interface="wl_output"/>
      <arg name="mat0" type="fixed"/>
      <arg name="mat1" type="fixed"/>
      <arg name="mat2" type="fixed"/>
      <arg name="mat3" type="fixed"/>
      <arg name="mat4" type="fixed"/>
      <arg name="mat5" type="fixed"/>
      <arg name="mat6" type="fixed"/>
      <arg name="mat7" type="fixed"/>
      <arg name="mat8" type="fixed"/>
    </request>

    <request name="commit">
      <description summary="commit the pending state">
        Commits the pending state(s) set by set_ctm_for_output.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        All objects created by the manager will still remain valid, until their
        appropriate destroy request has been called.

        The CTMs of all outputs will be reset to an identity matrix.
      </description>
    </request>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="invalid_matrix" value="0"
        summary="the matrix values are invalid."/>
    </enum>

    <event name="blocked" version="2">
      <description>
        This event is sent if another manager was bound by any client
        at the time the current manager was bound.
        Any set_ctm_for_output requests from a blocked manager will be
        silently ignored by the compositor.

        The client should destroy the manager after receiving this event.
      </description>
    </event>
  </interface>
</protocol>
