<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="hyprland_input_capture_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2025 Fl0w

    All rights reserved.

    Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without
    modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions are met:

    1. Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright notice, this
    list of conditions and the following disclaimer.

    2. Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright notice,
    this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the documentation
    and/or other materials provided with the distribution.

    3. Neither the name of the copyright holder nor the names of its
    contributors may be used to endorse or promote products derived from
    this software without specific prior written permission.

    THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS "AS IS"
    AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE
    IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE
    DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT HOLDER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE
    FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL
    DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR
    SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER
    CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY,
    OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE
    OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="Bridge input capture to the compositor">
	This protocol is a bridge of the XDG input capture to the compositor.
  </description>

  <interface name="hyprland_input_capture_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="manage input capture sessions">
      This interface allows to create an input capture session.
    </description>

    <request name="create_session">
      <description summary="create a input capture session">
        Create a input capture session.
      </description>

      <arg name="session" type="new_id" interface="hyprland_input_capture_v1"/>
      <arg name="handle" type="string"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

 <interface name="hyprland_input_capture_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="close reproduction of the xdg input capture portal">
	  Interface that is used to create barrier, and trigger capture and release of the pointer.
	  The inputs are sent through an EIS socket, when the cursor hit a barrier.
	  Barriers can only be placed on screen edges and need to be a straight line that cover one corner to another.
	</description>

	<request name="clear_barriers">
      <description summary="clear every barriers registered">
		Remove every barriers from the session, new barriers need to be send before calling enable again.
      </description>
  	</request>

	<request name="add_barrier">
	  <description summary="add one barrier">
	    Add one barrier to the current session, the barrier need to a line placed on the edge of the screen, and is a straight line from one corner to another.
   	  </description>

      <arg name="zone_set" type="uint" summary="The current zone_set" />
      <arg name="id" type="uint" summary="The zone id" />
      <arg name="x1" type="uint"/>
      <arg name="y1" type="uint"/>
      <arg name="x2" type="uint"/>
      <arg name="y2" type="uint"/>
	</request>

	<request name="enable">
	  <description summary="enable input capturing">
	    Enable the input capturing to be triggered by the cursor crossing a barrier.
	  </description>
  	</request>

	<request name="disable">
	  <description summary="disable input capturing">
	    Disable input capturing, the crossing of a barrier will not trigger anymore input capture.
	  </description>
  	</request>

	<request name="release">
	  <description summary="release input capturing">
	    Release input capturing, the input are not intercepted anymore and barrier crossing will activate it again.
		If x != -1 and y != -1 then the cursor is warped to the x and y coordinates.
	  </description>

      <arg name="activation_id" type="uint" summary="The activation id provided when activated is called" />
      <arg name="x"
        type="fixed"
        summary="the x position of the cursor" />
      <arg name="y" type="fixed"
        summary="the y position of the cursor" />
  	</request>

	<event name="eis_fd">
	  <description summary="eis file descriptor">
		This event provide the file descriptor of an eis socket where inputs will be sent when input capturing is active
	  </description>

      <arg name="fd" type="fd" summary="eis socket file descriptor" />
  	</event>

    <event name="disabled">
      <description summary="disable the session">
		Called when the application will not receive captured input. The application can call enable to request future input capturing
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="activated">
      <description summary="inputs has been captured">
		Called when the application is about to receive inputs
      </description>

      <arg name="activation_id"
        type="uint"
        summary="Same number used in eis start_emulating to allow synchronisation" />
      <arg name="x"
        type="fixed"
        summary="the x position of the cursor" />
      <arg name="y" type="fixed"
        summary="the y position of the cursor" />
      <arg name="barrier_id"
        type="uint"
        summary="the is of the barrier that have been triggered" />
    </event>

    <event name="deactivated">
	  <description summary="pointer motion">
        Called when input capture is stopped, and inputs are no longer sent to the application
	  </description>
      <arg name="activation_id"
        type="uint"
        summary="same activation id of the latest activated event" />
    </event>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="invalid_barrier_id" value="0"
        summary="The barrier id already exist"/>
      <entry name="invalid_barrier" value="1"
        summary="The barrier coordinates are invalid"/>
      <entry name="invalid_activation_id" value="2"
        summary="The activation id provided is invalid"/>
    </enum>
 </interface>
</protocol>
